Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series III: Children in Debt, 1987; 479162
  - "Children in Debt- Peru", circa 1987; cuid17667; 467404 (Box 27, Cassette ref649)
  - "8 Plus Interview with Economist", circa 1987; cuid17668; 467456 (Box 26, Cassette ref597)
  - "Alcade (Mayor) Barrantes Entrevista", circa 1987; cuid17669; 467451 (Box 26, Cassette ref602)
  - Argentina - footage of political event followed by scenes at an office of the National Food Program (Programa Alimentario Nacional), circa 1987; cuid17670; 467458 (Box 87, Cassette ref595, Box 82, Dvd ref595)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:00.
  - "Argentina #2 Street Talking about debt in Argentina", circa 1987; cuid17671; 479550 (Box 52, Cassette ref1208)
  - "Argentina #9 Visuals Neon Signs with Priest outside Church (Father Fascinelli)", circa 1987; cuid17672; 479551 (Box 52, Carton ref1209)
  - Barrantes, Alfonso: Interview, 1980s; cuid17673; 467457 (Box 87, Cassette ref596, Box 82, Dvd ref596)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:00.
    Augusto Alfonso Barrantes Lingan (1927-2000) was a socialist, labor lawyer, and mayor of Lima, Peru, from 1983-1987. He promoted the installation of kitchens in the city's slums and is known for his Vaso de Leche (Glass of Milk) campaign to ensure a daily glass of milk for every child in Lima.
  - Barrantes, milk campaign, other footage (Peru), circa 1987; cuid17674; 467455 (Box 87, Cassette ref598, Box 82, Dvd ref598)
  - Children in Debt, 1987; 2012.044; 593061; 2 Reels (Reel ref2156_01, Reel ref2156_02)
  - Children in Debt, 1987; 2013.014; 593066 (Reel ref2163)
  - Children in Debt, 1987; 2016.025; 593073 (Reel ref2168)
  - Barrantes, Alfonso, Milk Program, circa 1987; cuid17675; 479559 (Box 53, Cassette ref1217, Box 98, Dvd ref1217)
    Biographical / Historical
    Alfonso Barrantes was the mayor of Lima, Peru from 1984-1986.
    This video features footage of Peruvian politician Alfonso Barrantes touring a neighborhood in Lima, Peru and speaking to community members about his "Vaso de Leche" (Glass of Milk) program. The footage shows Barrantes speaking with community members and shows children drinking milk that the local government supplies to hungry children in the city. The video then features a teacher from a local school who explains how the program works. Many of the parents and educators featured in brief interviews mention that prior to the program the children in the village had never tasted milk.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:16.
  - "Cassette #3 Children in Debt", circa 1987; cuid17676; 479549 (Box 52, Cassette ref1207)
  - "Colombia in front of Plaza Bolivar, street interview, provivienda", circa 1987; cuid17677; 479554 (Box 52, Cassette ref1212)
  - "Colombia Monvita street visuals", circa 1987; cuid17678; 479557 (Box 52, Cassette ref1215)
  - García, Alan: Speech at Plaza de Armas, circa 1987; cuid17679; 479545 (Box 52, Cassette ref1203, Box 98, Dvd ref1203)
    This video features a speech by Peruvian President Alan García delivered at the Plaza de Armas sometime around the year 1987. García calls for unity among Latin American nations to fight against the crisis of foreign debt facing their countries. He criticizes wealthy nations in the north, international banks, creditors, and global financial organizations for taking advantage of Latin America. He argues that economic imperialism has led to Peru's fiscal crisis and has created extreme suffering and poverty in Peru. He contends that the only way to push back against the insurmountable debt payments is through unity among Latin American nations.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:21:56.
  - "Last Chile," "#1 Debt," and "Argentina", circa 1987; cuid17680; 479561 (Box 53, Cassette ref1219, Box 98, Dvd ref1219)
    This video begins with footage of a play. At minute 6:20 it changes to still images of a funeral procession. Then at minute 8:45 it changes to footage of on-the-street interviews in Argentina. Estela Bravo asks several individuals about the country's political situation and foreign debt. Several of the interviewees express frustration with the country's politics, arguing that there is high unemployment and little opportunity for the average citizen to create political change. Several individuals discuss the country's foreign debt. They question the government's ability to pay its debt and argue that average communities suffer in poverty in the meantime.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 0:22:08.
  - Bump: Mexico Visuals from Earthquake and Flower Girl, circa 1987; cuid17681; 479577 (Box 53, Cassette ref1235, Box 98, Dvd ref1235)
    The first portion of this video features footage of Mexico City following the 1985 earthquake that damaged large portions of the city. This footage does not contain any audio, but at times audio from unrelated content can be heard in the background. At minute 10:24 the video changes to footage of a young boy and girl who explain that they sell flowers to support their family and pay for school. During a brief interview with Estela Bravo the boy and girl also talk about other children who take drugs, although they say they do not. Bravo then interviews several children on the street who are taking drugs and asks them why they were attracted to drugs.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:13:22.
  - "Muestra de Niños Deudores in escuela cubana" (Piece/sample of Children in Debt in Cuban school), circa 1987; cuid17682; 479547 (Box 52, Cassette ref1205)
  - "Niños Escuela Mirando", circa 1987; cuid17683; 479543 (Box 52, Cassette ref1201)
  - Peru: Market and Street, circa 1987; cuid17684; 479567 (Box 53, Cassette ref1225, Box 98, Dvd ref1225)
    This video begins with background footage of a city in Peru. It focuses on homelessness and poverty in the city. At minute 11:24 the video changes to a Peruvian television program titled "Peru Imagen," which focuses on Peruvian history, culture, and landscapes.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:55:58.
  - "Provivienda Monjita", circa 1987; cuid17685; 479544 (Box 59, Cassette ref1202)
  - Street Interviews: Debt in Argentina, circa 1987; cuid17686; 479555 (Box 52, Cassette ref1213, Box 98, Dvd ref1213)
    This video features on-the-street interviews with Argentinians in the mid-1980s discussing the effect of foreign debt on their country. Many talk about the negative consequences of the debt on the country's children, poor, and elderly. Estela Bravo asks many members of the crowd what will happen if Argentina decides not to pay the debt. Many express their concern that the poor will suffer, and others discuss the possibility of Latin American countries collectively deciding not to pay the debt. One member of the crowd suggests that without unity among Latin American nations the decision to not pay would result in economic chaos. Several men in the crowd note that they have been out of work for many years, and others speculate about what will happen in Argentina's future.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:22.
  - Street Interviews: Peru / Ugarteche, Óscar: Beginning of Interview, circa 1987; cuid17687; 479556 (Box 52, Cassette ref1214, Box 98, Dvd ref1214)
    This video begins with on-the-street interviews with people in Peru discussing the effect of foreign debt on their country. Some individuals suggest that the debt is the fault of the investing class, while others express their concerns about the poor and the lack of investment in schools and social services. Several members of the crowd argue about whether Peru should pay the debt or whether they should attempt to resist foreign investors and the International Monetary Fund (IMF). In another short interview two boys tell the story of a child who was abandoned in a park by his impoverished parents. At minute 14:00 the video changes to an interview with Peruvian economist Óscar Ugarteche. He describes the conditions that led to the debt crisis in Peru and expresses his skepticism about the country's ability to pay the debt.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:21.
  - Ugarteche, Óscar: End of Interview / Alan García at the Plaza de Armas, circa 1987; cuid17688; 479566 (Box 53, Cassette ref1224, Box 98, Dvd ref1224)
    This video features the end of an interview with Peruvian economist Óscar Ugarteche. He discusses the economic crisis in Peru. In the interview, which was recorded in the mid-1980s, Ugarteche explains that the crisis had been building for over 10 years, and while the government focused on paying its international debt, it was not investing in the economy. He discusses the crisis of poverty, childhood hunger, and unemployment, and discusses economic changes that he thinks the country should take to emerge from the crisis. At minute 9:55 the video changes to a rally for Peruvian politician Alan García. Rally footage is incomplete and only contains short segments of his speech. The end of the video features footage of a concert.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:15:34.
  - Street Visuals, circa 1987; cuid17689; 479558 (Box 52, Cassette ref1216, Box 98, Dvd ref1216)
    This video features footage of children and families on the streets and in slums in a city in South America. The country in which the footage was filmed is unclear, but it features children washing car windshields and selling candies on the streets to earn money. It also features footage of families living on the street, children bathing in fountains, and children gathering water in a shanty town outside the city.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:38.
  - "Students, Police, Street (CH11)", circa 1984-1986; cuid18452; 479583 (Box 53, Cassette ref1241, Box Shared Tamiment 056, Dvd ref1241)
    This video features street footage and footage from a school in Bogotá, Colombia. It begins with two teachers at a kindergarten discussing the services they provide for poor children in the community. They describe the schools as a consistent source of food for local children. They also discuss high unemployment in the country and child malnutrition. The footage shows the children in the school singing songs and participating in a lesson on the alphabet. The video then changes to street footage of a slum outside of Bogotá where one of the teachers discusses the effects of foreign debt on the economy, the growth of slums, her Christian belief in Liberation Theology, and efforts to improve conditions in poor communities in the city. The video then cuts to footage of a different part of the city showing children selling goods on the street.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:29.
  - Peruvian New Reports: Drought, Unemployment, and Child Hunger, circa 1987; cuid17690; 479563 (Box 53, Cassette ref1221, Box 98, Dvd ref1221)
    This video features a series of clips from Peruvian news segments. The news segments feature reports on an extreme drought that destroyed crops and livestock in Peruvian agricultural regions, health conditions in poor communities, child hunger, an encampment of protesters seeking government assistance, and interviews with individuals about the state of the Peruvian economy. The footage features a segment titled "Enquesta," in which a reporter asks children what they ate for breakfast, and a number of the children reply that they had no breakfast at all.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:22.
  - "With Priest in Poor Neighborhood (Argentina)", circa 1987; cuid17691; 479546 (Box 52, Cassette ref1204, Box 98, Dvd ref1204)
    This video features footage of a village in Argentina. It begins with a guide describing the poverty within the community. Estela Bravo then interviews several men on the street who talk about closed factories and unemployment. She tours an area where an irrigation ditch is filled with garbage, and interviews several men who make money collecting and re-selling garbage for parts. She also interviews a young boy selling candy on the street to help feed his family. The guide later explains to Bravo that the community relies on schools as a consistent source of food for children, and blames Argentina's dictatorship for the debt and austerity that has impoverished the community.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:52.
  - "With Priest in Poor Neighborhood, Argentina #10", circa 1987; cuid17692; 479562 (Box 53, Cassette ref1220, Box 98, Dvd ref1220)
    This videos features footage of a community center in a poor village in Argentina that serves food and provides medical services to children in the community. The footage begins with an interview with the priest who supports the center. He discusses the problem of hunger in the community and explains that they feed 270 children. He explains that many parents are unemployed and cannot provide food for their children. The priest also shows Estela Bravo a baby at the community center, and explains that it is the child of a 13-year-old girl. He explains that young girls seek work as domestic servants, but those jobs were increasingly difficult to obtain and some turned to prostitution. The end of the video features an interview with two doctors at the center. They explain that they treated problems of malnutrition and parasitic infections, which were caused by unsanitary living conditions and lack of clean drinking water.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:34.
  - "With Priest in Poor Neighborhood, Argentina #11", circa 1987; cuid17693; 479560 (Box 53, Cassette ref1218, Box 98, Dvd ref1218)
    This video features a tour of a poor village in Argentina. It begins with footage of children sharing lunch in a school, and features shots of the streets and people in the village. The footage shows a priest speaking with people in the village, greeting them, and introducing them to Estela Bravo. Bravo asks several men and women about their country's foreign debt, and several speak about the extreme poverty in their community, the lack of jobs, and their dependence on government support. The priest shows Bravo a field fill with garbage and describes how men in the village sort the garbage and sell what they gather for parts. He explains that it is dangerous work, which contributes to many diseases in the community, and that the villagers live among the garbage daily.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:21:53.
- Series IV: A Conversation with García Márquez about his Friend Fidel, 2014; 593059
  - A Conversation with García Márquez about his Friend Fidel, 2014; cuid17694; 593060 (Box 73, Dvd 15)
    This is a full-length version of the documentary A Conversation with García Márquez about his Friend Fidel. This documentary is in Spanish with subtitles in English, and runs 32 minutes.
  - Bravo with Gabriel García Márquez, 2003; TW_TAM_616_ER_2 (Box Electronic Records, Folder TW_TAM_616_ER_2)
- Series V: Cuba/South Africa: After the Battle, 1990-1998; 479240
  Estela Bravo filmed After the Battle on location in Angola, South Africa, Namibia and Cuba following the 1998 surrender of South African troops in the Angolan war of independence. It was released in 1990, and in 1991 it won a Silver Apple Award for Best Film in War and Peace category at the National Educational Film and Video Festival in Oakland, California.
  Cuba/South Africa: After the Battle (Cuba y Sudáfrica: Después de la Batalla) relates the history of the Angola's war for independence and Cuba's contribution to the war efforts. The 58-minute documentary examines the motivations and consequences of the war. In addition to copies of the full-length documentary, this series contains footage shot in Angola and Cuba, which includes interviews with soldiers and families of those who were killed.
  - Cuba y Sudáfrica: Después de la Batalla, 1991; cuid17695; 468049 (Box 89, Cassette ref4, Box 75, Dvd ref4)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:58:00.
    This is a full-length feature of the film Cuba y Sudáfrica: Después de la Batalla. This film is in Spanish.
  - Cuba/South Africa: After the Battle, 1990; cuid17696; 590449; 3 videodiscs (dvd) (Box 73, Dvd 5, 6, 14)
    Content of these DVDs is born-digital. Advanced notice is required to access these materials.
  - Cuba/South Africa: After the Battle, circa 1990; cuid17697; 593064; 4 Reels (Reel ref2157_01, Reel ref2157_02, Reel ref2157_03, Reel ref2157_04)
  - Cuba/South Africa: After the Battle, 1990; cuid17698; 593067; 2 Reels (Reel ref2164_01, Reel ref2164_02)
  - Cuba/South Africa: After the Battle, 1990 July 31; cuid17699; 479241 (Box 45, Cassette ref978, Box 97, Dvd ref978)
    This video contains a complete version of the documentary Cuba/South Africa: After the Battle.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:58:51.
  - "After the Battle (English) 1st Cut", circa 1990; cuid17700; 467365 (Box 34, Cassette ref688)
  - "After the Battle (2nd Version)", circa 1990; cuid17701; 479653 (Box 65, Cassette ref1310)
  - "After the Battle 2nd Version R12", circa 1990; cuid17702; 479719 (Box 61, Cassette ref1372)
  - Papenfus, Johan: Interview, Airport, 1989 November 29; cuid17703; 467367 (Box 34, Cassette ref686)
  - "Papenfus leaving airport", circa 1990; cuid17704; 467294 (Box 42, Cassette ref759)
  - Footage: Returning from Angola "Barco, Travelling, Raul-Risquet discussion, Sala Universal", circa 1990; cuid17705; 479668 (Box 66, Cassette ref1325, Box 86, Dvd ref1325)
  - Footage: "Traveling, Poor Houses", circa 1990; cuid17706; 479616 (Box 55, Cassette ref1274, Box 98, Dvd ref1274)
    This video beings with footage filmed from the front seat of car traveling down a South African highway. It features footage of the car driving past poor communities on the outskirts of a city and then shows the car traveling into the city center. The second half of the video features of a hotel where diplomats from various countries including the United States, Soviet Union, and Cuba gathered for a meeting. The footage features several diplomats seated at a table in anticipation for the meeting.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:12:41.
  - Footage: "South Africa, parts for the final edition", circa 1990; cuid17707; 467806 (Box 89, Cassette ref247, Box 77, Dvd ref247)
    This video contains footage from After the Battle including interviews with individuals discussing Namibia and apartheid.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:25:15.
  - Cuba-South Africa (parts of), circa 1990; cuid17708; 479652 (Box 57, Cassette ref1309)
  - Cuba/South Africa Spanish, circa 1990; cuid17709; 467211 (Box 43, Cassette ref879)
  - Barco Second Cut, circa 1990; cuid17710; 479680 (Box 59, Cassette ref1337)
  - Angola Peace UN, circa 1990; cuid17711; 479741 (Box 49, Cassette ref1394)
  - Angola Restos J. Menindez, circa 1990; cuid17712; 479656 (Box 65, Cassette ref1313)
  - Interviews with various individuals (Cubans and South Africans) concerning the war in Angola, circa 1990; cuid17713; 467414 (Box 93, Cassette ref639, Box 82, Dvd ref639)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:00.
  - Papenfus, Johan: Interview "Bump", circa 1990; cuid284; 467366 (Box 34, Cassette ref687, Box 95, Dvd ref687)
    Johan Papenfus was a South African soldier who was injured in the South African Border War and held as a Cuban prisoner of war.
    This video contains various clips documenting the exchange of Cuban prisoners in Namibia for the South African soldier Johan Papenfus. The video begins with several short clips, and at minute 2:48 switches to an interview with Cuban soldiers talking about Papenfus. Minute 7:00-18:29 features an interview with Papenfus conducted by Estela Bravo. Beginning at minute 18:30 the video shows footage of Papenfus traveling back to South Africa, which makes up the bulk of the video. The video also contains short interviews with Cuban soldier Bernardo Heredia, who was held as a prisoner of war by South Africa and was one of several people exchanged for Papenfus. Two portions of the interview with Hererida begin at minute 22:15 and minute 44:32.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:58:01.
  - Interviews with South African soldiers concerning the war in Angola (South Africa), circa 1990; cuid17714; 467808 (Box 89, Cassette ref245, Box 77, Dvd ref245)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:50:17.
  - Park Central: Interviews, circa 1990; cuid17715; 479730 (Box 60, Cassette ref1383, Box 98, Dvd ref1383)
    This video features street footage of Havana, Cuba. It features footage of traffic and people riding bicycles. It also features footage of people fishing in Havana Bay. At minute 9:20 it features on-the-street interviews with several elderly men in a park. Estela Bravo asks them about Cubans living abroad, and the possibility of diplomatic relations improving between the United States and Cuba. She also asks them how the blockade has affected their lives.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:16:23.
  - Park Central: Interviews about War in Angola, circa 1990; cuid17716; 479735 (Box 60, Cassette ref1388, Box 98, Dvd ref1388)
    The first 30 minutes of this video features interviews with Cubans in the Parque Central in Havana. Estela Bravo asks about Cuba's support of Angola's war against South Africa, and the Cuban troops coming home from the war. Members of the crowd describe their understanding of the war and Cuba's reason for supporting the Angola. Many express their approval of Cuba's role in the war and speak generally about racial equality and the need to fight against apartheid in South Africa. One man discusses his reason for not volunteering to fight, and he argues with many others in the crowd. The second half of this video features an assortment of clips from footage in South Africa including a musical concert, short interviews with South Africans and Angolans, crowd footage, and Cubans who fought in Namibia. When footage is in English, Bravo speaks over the footage translating into Spanish.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:32.
  - Reception for Former Prisoners - Angola, circa 1990; cuid17717; 467225 (Box 41, Cassette ref828)
  - Images of the War in Angola, 1998 November 18; cuid17718; 467817 (Box 10, Cassette ref236, Box 97, Dvd ref236)
    This video begins with edited portions of the documentary Cuba/South Africa: After the Battle. The video also features some raw footage including Fidel Castro discussing military forces and strategy in Angola, and footage of Cuban and Namibian troops in training exercises.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:13:16.
  - Angola, circa 1990; cuid17719; 467318 (Box 40, Cassette ref735)
  - "Cuba South Africa", circa 1990; cuid17720; 467425 (Box 32, Cassette ref628)
  - "Cuba/Sud Africa", circa 1990; cuid17721; 467420 (Box 32, Cassette ref633)
  - "Cuba-Sud Africa", circa 1990; cuid17722; 467374 (Box 31, Cassette ref679)
  - "Documental Estelo Bravo Edicion, Bump 9", circa 1990; cuid17723; 467233 (Box 41, Cassette ref820)
  - "Documental Estelo Bravo Edicion, Bump 5", circa 1990; cuid17724; 467232 (Box 41, Cassette ref821)
  - Bump 2, circa 1990; cuid17725; 467304 (Box 42, Cassette ref749)
  - "Angola Peace Bump 3", circa 1990; cuid17726; 467229 (Box 41, Cassette ref824)
  - Bump 6, circa 1990; cuid17727; 467305 (Box 42, Cassette ref748)
  - "After the Battle ECITVFAR", circa 1990; cuid17728; 467230 (Box 41, Cassette ref860)
  - Cacahual Memorial, circa 1990; cuid17730; 479731 (Box 60, Cassette ref1384, Box 98, Dvd ref1384)
    Historical Note
    El Cacahual Mausoleum is a monument and resting place of Cuban military commander Antonio Maceo outside of Havana. It has become a national symbol to honor those who died during military service.